So, I was in the hospital for a long time.
اذا، كنت في المستشفى لمدة طويلة.
And a few years after I left, I went back,
وبعد أن غادرت ببضع سنوات، عدت مجددا،
and the chairman of the burn department was very excited to see me --
ورئيس قسم الحرائق كان متحمسا لرؤيتي --
said, "Dan, I have a fantastic new treatment for you."
قال، "دان، لدي علاج جديد رائع لك"
I was very excited. I walked with him to his office.
كنت متحمسا للغاية. سرت معه إلى مكتبه.
And he explained to me that, when I shave,
وشرح لي أنه، حين أحلق،
I have little black dots on the left side of my face where the hair is,
تكون لدي نقط سوداء صغيرة في الجهة اليسرى من وجهي حيث يوجد الشعر،
but on the right side of my face
لكن في الجهة اليمنى من وجهي
I was badly burned so I have no hair,
كنت مصابا بحروق شديدة وبالتالي ليس لدي شعر،
and this creates lack of symmetry.
وهذا يخلق نقصا في التناسق.
And what's the brilliant idea he had?
وما هي الفكرة الذكية التي كانت لديه؟
He was going to tattoo little black dots
كان سيوشم نقطا صغيرة سوداء
on the right side of my face
في الجهة اليمنى من وجهي
and make me look very symmetric.
فيجعلني أبدو في غاية التناسق.
It sounded interesting. He asked me to go and shave.
يبدو الأمر مثيرا للإهتمام. طلب مني أن أذهب وأحلق.
Let me tell you, this was a strange way to shave,
دعوني أخبركم، كانت تلك طريقة غريبة في الحلاقة،
because I thought about it
لأنني فكرت في الأمر
and I realized that the way I was shaving then
وتيقنت أن الطريقة التي سأحلق بها آنذلك
would be the way I would shave for the rest of my life --
ستكون الطريقة التي سأحلق بها لبقية حياتي --
because I had to keep the width the same.
لأنه علي أن أحافظ على نفس العرض.
When I got back to his office,
حين عدت إلى مكتبه،
I wasn't really sure.
لم أكن في الواقع متأكدا.
I said, "Can I see some evidence for this?"
قلت، "هل لي أن أرى بعض الأدلة على هذا؟"
So he showed me some pictures
فأراني بعض الصور
of little cheeks with little black dots --
لخدود صغيرة بنقط سوداء صغيرة --
not very informative.
لم تكن غاية في الإفادة.
I said, "What happens when I grow older and my hair becomes white?
قلت، "ما الذي يحدث حين أتقدم في العمر ويصير شعري أبيض؟
What would happen then?"
ما الذي سيحصل حينئد؟"
"Oh, don't worry about it," he said.
فقال "أوه، لا تقلق بخصوص ذلك،".
"We have lasers; we can whiten it out."
"لدينا ليزر؛ بإمكاننا جعله أبيض."
But I was still concerned,
لكنني كنت لا أزال قلقا،
so I said, "You know what, I'm not going to do it."
فقلت، "تعرف ماذا، لن أقوم بذلك."
And then came one of the biggest guilt trips of my life.
وآنذاك بدأت أحد أكبر رحلة شعور بالذنب في حياتي.
This is coming from a Jewish guy, all right, so that means a lot.
وهذا كلام يصدر عن شخص يهودي، حسنا، فذلك يعني الكثير.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And he said, "Dan, what's wrong with you?
فقال، "دان، ما خطبك؟
Do you enjoy looking non-symmetric?
أتفضل الظهور بشكل غير متناسق؟
Do you have some kind of perverted pleasure from this?
هل يجعلك هذا تحس بنوع من اللذة المنحرفة؟
Do women feel pity for you
هل يشعر النسوة بالشفقة عليك
and have sex with you more frequently?"
فيضاجعنك بشكل أكثر تكررا؟"
None of those happened.
لا شيء من ذلك حصل.
And this was very surprising to me,
وهذا كان مفاجئا لي،
because I've gone through many treatments --
لأنني خضعت للكثير من العلاجات --
there were many treatments I decided not to do --
هناك الكثير من العلاجات قررت عدم الخضوع لها --
and I never got this guilt trip to this extent.
ولم أتعرض لرحلة شعور بذنب بهذا المستوى من قبل.
But I decided not to have this treatment.
لكنني قررت عدم الخضوع لهذا العلاج.
And I went to his deputy and asked him, "What was going on?
وتوجهت نحو نائبه فسألته، "ما الذي يحدث؟
Where was this guilt trip coming from?"
من أين جاءت رحلة الشعور بالذنب هذه؟"
And he explained that they have done this procedure on two patients already,
فشرح لي أنهم أجروا العملية على مريضين من قبل،
and they need the third patient for a paper they were writing.
وهم في حاجة إلى مريض ثالث من أجل ورقة علمية كانوا يكتبونها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now you probably think that this guy's a schmuck.
لعلكم الآن تعتقدون أن ذلك الشخص وضيع.
Right, that's what he seems like.
صحيح، هذا ما يبدو عليه.
But let me give you a different perspective on the same story.
لكن دعوني أعطيكم منظورا مختلفا لنفس القصة.
A few years ago, I was running some of my own experiments in the lab.
قبل بضع سنوات ، كنت أجري بعض تجاربي في المختبر.
And when we run experiments,
وحين نجري التجارب،
we usually hope that one group will behave differently than another.
نتمنى عادة أن تتصرف مجموعة بخلاف الأخرى.
So we had one group that I hoped their performance would be very high,
وهكذا كانت لدينا مجموعة تمنيت أن يكون أداؤهم عاليا جدا،
another group that I thought their performance would be very low,
ومجموعة أخرى اعتقدت أن أداءهم سيكون متدنيا جدا.
and when I got the results, that's what we got --
وحين حصلت على النتائج، كان ذلك ما حصل --
I was very happy -- aside from one person.
كنت في غاية السعادة -- باستثناء شخص واحد.
There was one person in the group
كان هناك شخص واحد في المجموعة
that was supposed to have very high performance
كان من المفترض أن يكون أداؤه عاليا
that was actually performing terribly.
كان أداؤه في الواقع رديئا.
And he pulled the whole mean down,
فأنزل المتوسط بكامله،
destroying my statistical significance of the test.
مخربا القيمة الإحصائية للإختبار.
So I looked carefully at this guy.
وبالتالي نظرت بعناية لهذا الشخص.
He was 20-some years older than anybody else in the sample.
كان في العشرينيات من عمره أكبر ممن سواه في المجموعة.
And I remembered that the old and drunken guy
وتذكرت أن الشخص الكبير المخمور
came one day to the lab
قد جاء في أحد الأيام إلى المختبر
wanting to make some easy cash
منتظرا الحصول على بعض الكسب السريع
and this was the guy.
وهذا كان ذلك الشخص.
"Fantastic!" I thought. "Let's throw him out.
"رائع!" فكرت في ذلك. "دعونا نطرده.
Who would ever include a drunken guy in a sample?"
من قد يضمن شخصا مخمورا في عينة؟"
But a couple of days later,
لكن بعض بضعة أيام،
we thought about it with my students,
فكرت في الأمر مع طلبتي،
and we said, "What would have happened if this drunken guy was not in that condition?
وقلنا، "ما الذي قد يحصل إن لم يكن الشخص المخمور في ذلك الوضع؟
What would have happened if he was in the other group?
ما الذي قد يحصل لو أنه كان في المجموعة الأخرى؟
Would we have thrown him out then?"
أكنا سنطرده آنذاك؟"
We probably wouldn't have looked at the data at all,
قد لا نكون حتى نظرنا إلى البيانات،
and if we did look at the data,
وإن نظرنا إلى البيانات،
we'd probably have said, "Fantastic! What a smart guy who is performing this low,"
ربما نقول، "رائع! ياله من شخص ذكي بأداء ضعيف،"
because he would have pulled the mean of the group lower,
لأنه سيخفض متوسط المجموعة أقل،
giving us even stronger statistical results than we could.
معطيا إيانا نتائج إحصائية أقوى مما كنا نستطيع.
So we decided not to throw the guy out and to rerun the experiment.
فقررنا عدم طرد الشخص وإعادة التجربة.
But you know, these stories,
لكن تعرفون، هذه القصص،
and lots of other experiments that we've done on conflicts of interest,
والكثير من التجارب الأخرى التي أجريناها بخصوص تضارب المصالح،
basically kind of bring two points
تبرز أمرين أساسا
to the foreground for me.
بالنسبة لي.
The first one is that in life we encounter many people
أولها أنه في الحياة نصادف الكثير من الناس
who, in some way or another,
الذين، بطريقة أو بأخرى،
try to tattoo our faces.
يحاولون وشم وجوهنا.
They just have the incentives that get them to be blinded to reality
لديهم فقط الحوافز التي تعميهم عن الواقع
and give us advice that is inherently biased.
فيعطوننا نصيحة منحازة أصلا.
And I'm sure that it's something that we all recognize,
وأنا متأكد أنه أمر نعرفه جميعا،
and we see that it happens.
ونرى أنه يحصل.
Maybe we don't recognize it every time,
ربما لا نتعرف عليه في كل مرة،
but we understand that it happens.
لكننا نفهم أنه يحصل.
The most difficult thing, of course, is to recognize
الأمر الأكثر صعوبة، بالطبع، هو معرفة
that sometimes we too
أنه أحيانا نحن كذلك
are blinded by our own incentives.
تعمينا حوافزنا.
And that's a much, much more difficult lesson to take into account.
وذاك درس أكثر صعوبة أن يؤخذ بعين الإعتبار.
Because we don't see how conflicts of interest work on us.
لأننا لا نرى كيف يعمل تضارب المصالح فينا.
When I was doing these experiments,
حين كنت أقوم بهذه التجارب،
in my mind, I was helping science.
في ذهني، كنت أخدم العلم.
I was eliminating the data
كنت أزيل البيانات
to get the true pattern of the data to shine through.
للحصول على نمط حقيقي حتى تتألق البيانات.
I wasn't doing something bad.
لم أكن أقوم بأمر سيء.
In my mind, I was actually a knight
في ذهني، كنت في الحقيقة فارسا
trying to help science move along.
يحاول مساعدة العلم على التقدم.
But this was not the case.
لكن ذلك لم يكن ما يحصل.
I was actually interfering with the process with lots of good intentions.
كنت في الواقع أتدخل في العملية بالكثير من النوايا الحسنة.
And I think the real challenge is to figure out
وأعتقد أن التحدي الحقيقي هو معرفة
where are the cases in our lives
أين هي الحالات في حياتنا
where conflicts of interest work on us,
التي ينطبق فيها تضارب المصالح علينا،
and try not to trust our own intuition to overcome it,
ومحاولة عدم الوثوق بحدسنا لتجاوز ذلك،
but to try to do things
لكن محاولة القيام بأشياء
that prevent us from falling prey to these behaviors,
لتجنيبنا من الوقوع فريسة لهذه التصرفات،
because we can create lots of undesirable circumstances.
لأننا نستطيع أن نخلق الكثير من الظروف الغير مرغوب فيها.
I do want to leave you with one positive thought.
أريد أن أترككم مع فكرة إيجابية.
I mean, this is all very depressing, right --
أقصد، كل هذا كئيب للغاية، صحيح --
people have conflicts of interest, we don't see it, and so on.
الناس لديهم تضارب في المصالح، لا نراه، وما إلى ذلك.
The positive perspective, I think, of all of this
أعتقد أن الأمر الإيجابي في كل هذا
is that, if we do understand when we go wrong,
هو أنه، إن استوعبنا حين نكون مخطئين،
if we understand the deep mechanisms
إن استوعبنا الآليات العميقة
of why we fail and where we fail,
حول لماذا نفشل وأين نفشل،
we can actually hope to fix things.
يمكننا في الواقع أن نأمل إصلاح الأمور.
And that, I think, is the hope. Thank you very much.
وأعتقد أن هذا هو الأمل. شكرا جزيلا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)